STEVEN HAWKINS PAPERS (APAP188) 1991-2003
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Steven Hawkins Papers1991-2003
nam_apap188
Hawkins, Steven W.
3.2
Records of Steven W. Hawkins's tenure as Executive Director of the National Coalition Against the Death Penalty. The papers include extensive minutes of board meetings, speeches, travel arrangements, fundraising and reception notes, and pamphlets and other papers relating to his attendance at various board and committee meetings with related organizations.
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Biographical Sketch
Steven W. Hawkins was the executive director of the National Coalition Against the Death Penalty (now known as the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty) based in Washington, D.C. Hawkins has worked as an advocate for civil and human rights representing persons under death sentence in state, federal, and military courts across the country. He has provided commentary on the death penalty on The Today Show, CNN, Court TV, The NewsHour with Jim Lehrer, and other major television news programs. Hawkins was selected as a Next Generation Leadership Fellow by the Rockefeller Foundation and received the Thurgood Marshall Award from the Bar Association of New York for his advocacy on behalf of persons under sentence of death. His profession affiliations include the National Conference of Black Lawyers and the Center for International Studies at New York University, where he served on the board of trustees [Open Society Institute and Soros Foundations Network, "Past Events: OSI Forum: Supreme Decisions -- Re-Thinking the Death Penalty", http://www.soros.org/initiatives/justice/events/deathpenalty_20020718/event_biography_folder_initiative_view Accessed 14 September 2006].
The National Coalition Against the Death Penalty was started in 1976 and is a national organization dedicated to providing advocacy for inmates and other people affected by death penalty laws, such as families of prisoners and victims. The National Coalition Against the Death Penalty seeks to provide information to community members on death penalty issues, legal help for inmates to have their sentences either commuted or exonerated, encouragement for the media to provide accurate coverage of the death penalty, analysis and lobbying for legislative bodies to encourage them to abolish the death penalty, assisting local death penalty groups in their efforts and encouraging the global community to abolish the death penalty. The National Coalition Against the Death Penalty believes that the death penalty should be abolished based on four principles: that capital punishment denies the dignity and worth of every human being by preventing them from personal repentance and transformation, that capital punishment is irreversible but frequently fallible (as seen through DNA evidence), that capital punishment is consistently applied with racial and class prejudices against the defendants, and that capital punishment is a basic violation of international human rights laws. For additional information about the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty consult the organization's website at http://www.ncadp.org/about_us.html.
Scope and Content Information
Steven Hawkins and his staff created these papers during his tenure as Executive Director of the National Coalition Against the Death Penalty (now known as the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty). The papers contain meeting subject files that include extensive minutes of board meetings, speeches, fundraising, reception notes, pamphlets, and other papers relating to his attendance at various board and committee meetings with related organizations, such as the Death Penalty Information Center and Amnesty International. The papers also contain copies of police reports, witness and investigator statements, and defendant testimony regarding the cases of certain high-profile death row inmates, such as Mumia Abu-Jamal, Delma Banks Jr., Wilburn Dobbs, Reginald Clemons, Clarence Allen Lackey, T. Makawanyane and Mchunu, Kenneth Reams. and Keith Versie. These inmate files were retained by Steven Hawkins and his staff in order to provide legal advocacy in court hearings to obtain commutation, clemency, or exoneration for these inmates.
The papers lack full biographical information about Mr. Hawkins, with the exception of a few mentions of his wife Wanda and details about his previous experience as a lawyer in Washington, D.C. The papers give many biographical details about the death row inmates included and some detail about some of the witnesses and investigators. Other than the founding date of the National Coalition Against the Death Penalty, no details exist in these papers as to the organization's general history before the mid-1990s, when Hawkins joined the staff.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Meeting Subject Files, 1995-2003
Series 2: Case Files, 1991-2002
.
Series arrangement statement: SUNY will complete.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Steven Hawkins in December 2004.
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found in the subject guides for the National Death Penalty Archive and Criminal Justice and Prisons. Of particular note in the National Death Penalty Archive are the papers of Hugo A. Bedau (APAP-199) and Bill Pelke (APAP-205), board
Access
Access to these records is unrestricted.
Subject and Genre Headings
Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Hawkins, Steven W.; Abu-Jamal, Mumia.; Banks, Delma, Jr.; Reams, Kenneth.; Versie, Keith.; Corporate Death Penalty Information Center (U.S.); Amnesty International.; Capital punishment.; Death row inmates.
Container List
- Meeting Subject Files, 1995-2003; 1; 2
  This series includes extensive minutes of board meetings, speeches, fundraising, correspondence, notes, pamphlets, biographies of speakers, and other papers relating to Hawkins' attendance at various board and committee meetings, rallies, and conferences Hawkins attended as Executive Director of the National Coalition Against the Death Penalty. These events were sponsored by related institutional, regional, national, and international organizations such as law schools, New Yorkers Against the Death Penalty, the Death Penalty Information Center, Amnesty International, and many others. A complete list of meetings is included in the box and folder list.
  Arranged chronologically by meeting.
  - Meetings, 1995 July-1995 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Japanese Delegation to Death Penalty Organizations, 1995 July
    - Howard University School of Law, Training for Legal Observers of the Million Man March, 1995 September
    - Foundation Meeting, William J. Brennan Project, 1995 October
    - University of Michigan Law School Symposium, Journal of Race and Law, "Toward a New Civil Rights Vision", 1995 October
    - Boston Fundraiser, 1995 October
    - Missouri Coalition Against the Death Penalty, 1995 October
    - American Society of International Law, Young Members Interest Group, "Pursuing a Career in the Field of Human Rights? Learn How to Develop Professional Contacts and Opportunities", 1995 October
    - New York Capital Defender Training, 1995 October
    - Arkansas Coalition Meeting, 1995 November
    - National Association of Investigators, 1995 November
    - Ohio Criminal Defense Lawyers, 1995 December
  - Meetings, 1996 January-1996 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - International Commission of Jurists Delegation to the United States, 1996 January
    - University of Utah, 1996 February
    - Sister Helen Prejean Reception, New York City, 1996 February
    - Interfaith Impact, 1996 March
    - American University, 1996 March
    - Bruderhof Town Hall Meeting, Philadelphia, 1996 March
    - Army Capital Litigation Seminar, 1996 March
    - University of Dayton, 1996 March
  - Meetings, 1996 March-1996 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meetings, 1996 March-1996 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Student Coalition Against the Death Penalty New York University, 1996 March-1996 April
    - Tikkun National Summit on Ethics/Meaning, 1996 April
    - Westchester Community College, 1996 April
    - Black Student Leadership Network Reception, 1996 April
    - Black Allied Law Students Association, 1996 April
    - Ohioans To Stop Executions, 1996 April
    - Ohio Death Penalty Seminar, 1996 May
    - Magnolia Bar Association, Buloxi, Mississippi, 1996 May
    - National Convocation of Jail and Prison Ministry, 1996 May
    - Minnesota Advocates for Human Rights, Minneapolis, MN, 1996 May
  - Meetings, 1996 June-1996 December (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Furman and Gregg Fast and Vigil at the United States Supreme Court, 1996 July
    - Death Penalty Institute, Montgomery AL, 1996 July
    - National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers Annual Meeting, 1996 August
    - Death Penalty Information Center, 1996 July
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Legal Defense and Education Fund 17th Annual Capital Punishment Training Conference, 1996 July
    - Southern Human Rights Organization Conference, Oxford, MS, 1996 September
    - National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty and 28th Annual National Conference of Black Lawyers, 1996 October
    - Harvard University Institute of Politics Tribute to Ronald H. Brown, 1996 November
    - National Youth Leadership Forum on the Law and the Constitution, 1996 November
    - Ohio Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers, 1996 October-1996 November
    - Journey of Hope, 1996 October
    - Death Penalty Information Center, 1996 December
  - Meetings, 1996 December-1997 March (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Meeting with Arkadiy Sosnov of the Russian Newspaper Ogonyok, 1997 January
    - Amnesty International, 1996 December-1997 February
    - American Civil Liberties Conference, 1997 February
    - Citizens United for Alternatives to the Death Penalty Conference, 1997 February-1997 March
  - Meetings, 1997 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Texas Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, Central Texas Chapter, 1997 March
    - United Methodist Church, 1997 March
    - University Neighborhood Initiative, 1996 January-1997 February
    - Italian Consulate, 1997 March
    - Open Society Institute and Soros Justice Fellowships, 1997 March
    - Fordham University School of Law Symposium on Cesare Beccaria's "Of Crimes and Punishment" and Its Present Impact and Hands off Cain Symposium, 1997 March
    - Maryland Criminal Defense Attorney's Association, 1997 February
    - Skadden Fellowship Foundation, 1997 February
    - National Interreligious Task Force of Criminal Justice, 1997 March
  - Meetings, 1997 April (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Vassar Gathering, 1997 March-1997 April
    - Nation Town Hall Meeting, 1997 April
    - University of Maryland Eastern Shore, 1997 April
    - Lyndh v. Murphy United States Supreme Court, 1997 April
    - Georgetown University Law Center, 1997 April
    - National Public Policy Summit, 1997 January; 1997 April
    - Amnesty International, Atlanta, GA, 1997 April
  - Meetings, 1997 May-1997 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Coalition Against Racism & the Death Penalty, Philadelphia, 1997 May
    - Law Clerks Speakers Program, 1997 February; 1997 July
    - American University, 1997 October
    - Drexel University Death Penalty in Philadelphia Conference, 1997 October
    - National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers, 1997 October
    - Soros Justice Fellowships, 1997 November
    - Cochran Fundraiser, 1997 November
    - New Orleans, 1997 November
    - People's International Tribunal for Justice for Mumia Abu Jamal, 1997 December
    - European Parliament, 1997 December
  - Meetings, 1998 January-1998 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 1998 January
    - The College of William and Mary, Institute of the Bill of Rights Law, Student Division, Juvenile Adjudication Seminar, 1998 February
    - Howard University School of Law, 1998 February
    - Law Clerks Speakers Program, 1998 February
    - University of San Francisco Law Review and Coleman Advocates for Children and Youth, Juvenile Justice: A Critical Response Seminar, 1998 February
    - Death Penalty Moratorium, 1998 February
    - Georgetown University United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child, Washington, DC, 1998 February
    - Hands off Cain, the United Nations Against the Death Penalty Convention, Geneva, Switzerland, 1998 March
    - General Board of Church and Society of the United Methodist Church, 1998 March
    - University of South Carolina, 1998 April
    - Open Society Institute and the Center on Crime, Communities and Culture, 1998 April
    - Amnesty International Death Penalty Institute, 1998 April
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 1998 April
    - Fundraising School Training New York, 1998 April
    - City Bar Association of New York, 1998 April
  - Meetings, 1998 May-1998 September (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Judge Higginbotham Law Clerk Reunion, 1998 May
    - Missourians to Abolish the Death Penalty, 1998 June
    - National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty New York Reception, 1998 June
    - Annual Fast and Vigil to Abolish the Death Penalty, United States Supreme Court, 1998 June
    - United Nations International Criminal Tribunal for Yugoslavia, The Hague, Netherlands, 1998 June
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 1998 July
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Legal Defense Fund Capital Punishment Conference, 1998 July
    - Congressional Black Caucus, 1998 September
  - Meetings, 1998 September-1998 November (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Critical Resistance Conference, 1998 September
    - Leadership Summit, 1998 October
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, New York City, 1998 October
    - War Resistance League Conference, Maryland, 1998 October
    - National Association for Public Interest Law Career Fair and Conference, University of Maryland, 1998 November
    - Ford Foundation Program, New York City, 1998 November
    - National Crime Policy Conference, Bethesda, MD, 1998 November
    - Soros Fellowship Selection, 1998 November
  - Meetings, 1998 November (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - National Conference on Wrongful Convictions, Chicago, 1998 November
    - Caring for Prisoners, Open Society Institute, New York Academy of Medicine, New York City, 1998 November
    - Next Generation Leadership Fellows, Greenville, MS, 1998 November
    - University of Maryland, 1998 November
    - Religious Organizing Meeting, National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, 1998 November
  - Meetings, 1998 December (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - George Mavety Meeting, 1998 December
    - Princeton University, 1998 December
    - Executive Director Evaluation, 1998 December
    - Southern Human Rights Organizers' Conference, 1998 December
    - American Philosophical Association, Washington, D.C., 1998 December
  - Meetings, 1999 January-1999 February (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 1999 January
    - Bob Domer Memorial Symposium, 1999 January
    - Law Clerks Speakers Program, Washington, D.C., 1999 February
    - Pat Robertson and Bianca Jagger, Executive Clemency Panel, City Bar of New York, 1999 February
    - Leeza Show, Los Angeles, 1999 February
    - Mumia Organizing Meeting, Washington, D.C., 1999 February
    - Close Up Foundation, Washington, D.C., 1999 February
    - A. Leon Higginbotham Memorial Service, Philadelphia, 1999 February
    - Soros Justice Fellowship Reception, New York City, 1999 February
  - Meetings, 1999 March (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Sentencing Project, Washington, D.C., 1999 March
    - Dance Away the Winter Blues for Healing Connection, 1999 March
    - New York University Fellowship Selection, 1999 March
    - New York Abolition Meeting, 1999 March
    - American Friends Service Committee, Boston, 1999 March
    - Howard University Law School, 1999 March
    - Interview with Matheiu Castagnet La Croix Newspaper, France, 1999 March
    - Mumia Abu-Jamal Symposium, Philadelphia, 1999 March
  - Meetings, 1999 April-1999 June (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Religious Organizing Project, San Antonio, TX, 1999 April
    - Nortel Networks Cherry Blossom Race, 1999 April
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 1999 April
    - Missouri Coalition Meeting, Columbia, MO, 1999 April
    - National Legal Aid and Defender Association, Criminal Justice Meeting, Washington, D.C., 1999 April
    - Rockefeller Next Generation Leadership, Taos, NM, 1999 April
    - Pen Prison Writer Program, New York City, 1999 April
    - Bruderhof Gathering, Rifton, NY, 1999 May
    - Legislative Strategy Call, 1999 May
    - Leadership Summit Meeting, Washington, D.C., 1999 June
    - Cure National Conference, Washington, D.C., 1999 June
    - Amnesty International Conference, Bermuda, 1999 June
    - Columbia University, 1999 June
  - Meetings, 1999 June-1999 July (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - United States Senate Meeting, 1999 June
    - Peace Watch Ireland, 1999 June-1999 July
    - Abolition Action Committee, 1999 June-1999 July
    - Strategic Planning Meeting, 1999 July
    - Seniors Group Meeting, Washington, D.C., 1999 July
    - National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers, Washington, D.C., 1999 July
  - Meetings, 1999 July-1999 October (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 1999 July
    - Airlie Conference, Virginia, 1999 July
    - National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Board Meeting, 1999 July
    - Foundation Meeting, Philadelphia, 1999 September
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 1999 October
  - Meetings, 1999 October-1999 December (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - German Delegation, 1999 October
    - Amnesty International, Sweden, 1999 October
    - International Abolition Conference, 1999 October
    - American Bar Association, 1999 October
    - Book Anthology Project, 1999 November
    - New York University School of Law, Lawyers Committee on Human Rights, 1999 November
    - Jefferson Debating Society, University of Virginia, 1999 November
    - Alumni Root-Tilden-Kern Graduates, New York University, 1999 November
    - Soros Fellowship Selection, 1999 November
    - New York University School of Law Program, 1999 November
    - Howard Law School, 1999 November
    - American Civil Liberties Union, 1999 November
    - Center for International Studies, New York University School of Law, 1999 November
    - Justice Project Meeting, Washington, D.C., 1999 December
  - Meetings, 2000 January (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Director's Evaluation, 2000 January
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 2000 January
    - International Committee to Save the Life of Mumia-Abu-Jamal, 2000 January
    - American University, 2000 January
    - Death Penalty Working Group Meeting, 2000 January
    - National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Board Meeting, 2000 January
  - Meetings, 2000 February (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bryn Mawr College, 2000 February
    - National Youth Advocate Conference, Kansas, 2000 February
    - National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Mid-Winter Conference, New Orleans, 2000 February
  - Meetings, 2000 March (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Staff Meeting, 2000 March
    - Grant Writing Seminar, New York City, 2000 March
    - Columbia Human Rights Conference, 2000 March
    - Open Society Institute, 2000 March
    - University of Virginia School of Law Public Service Center Conference, 2000 March
    - Grant Writing Seminar, New York City, 2000 March
    - National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Conference Call, 2000 March
    - TPW/NGL Youth Collaborative Steering Committee Meeting, 2000 March
    - National Newspaper Publishers Association, The Black Press of America Awards Dinner, 2000 March
    - NAACP Conference, Pittsburgh, 2000 March
  - Meetings, 2000 April-2000 June (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Columbia Conference, Race and the Criminal Justice System, 2000 April
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 2000 April
    - National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Board Meeting, 2000 April
    - New York Death Penalty Conference, 2000 April
    - Musgrove Retreat, 2000 June
    - Rockefeller Alumni Association, New York City, 2000 June
  - Meetings, 2000 July (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Bringing Human Rights Home, Columbia University, 2000 July
    - Moratorium Discussion Meeting, 2000 July
    - San Francisco, 2000 July
    - World Conference Against Racism, Oakland, CA, 2000 July
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 2000 July
    - Death Penalty Protest, Washington, D.C., 2000 July
  - Meetings, 2000 August-2000 October (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - New Voices Mentors Orientation, 2000 August
    - National Medical Association, Washington, D.C., 2000 August
    - Center for Constitutional Rights, 2000 August
    - Texas Stand Down Meeting, Austin, TX, 2000 August
    - Riverside Church Program, New York City, 2000 September
    - CBC Weekend Program, 2000 September
    - Mumia Program, Boston, MA, 2000 September
    - Open Society Institute, New York City, 2000 October
    - National Conference of Black Lawyers, Selma, AL, 2000 October
    - Bringing Human Rights Home, Warrenton, VA, 2000 October
    - World Conference on Racism, World Organization Against Torture, 2000 October
    - National Coalition of Blacks for Reparations in America Litigation Strategy, 2000 October
    - Death Penalty Information Center Board Meeting, 2000 October
  - Meetings, 2000 November-2001 January (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Moratorium Town Meeting North Carolina Central University, 2000 November
    - Soros Justice Fellowship, 2000 November
    - Puffin Gallery Program, New York City, 2000 November
    - Southern Human Rights Organizer's Conference III, Atlanta, GA, 2000 December
    - University Park, MD Church of the Brethren Christmas Sharing Fair, 2000 December
    - Moratorium 2000 Event, 2000 December
    - Next Generation Leadership Youth Collaborative, 2001 January
  - Meetings, 2001 March-2001 April (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Willie Fisher Execution, Raleigh, NC, 2001 March
    - National Newsmaker Award, 2001 March
    - Next Generation Leadership Planning Meeting, 2001 March
    - Center for International Studies, New York University Law School, 2001 March